I haven't told many people this,
لم أشارك ما سأقوله مع الكثيرين،
but in my head, I've got
لكن في ذهني يوجد هناك
thousands of secret worlds all going on
الآلاف من العوالم السرية الناشطة
all at the same time.
في الوقت ذاته.
I am also autistic.
أنا أيضا متوحدة.
People tend to diagnose autism
البشر يميلون إلى تشخيص التوحد
with really specific check-box descriptions,
بوسائل وأوصاف محددة،
but in reality, it's a whole variation as to what we're like.
ولكن في الواقع، تختلف كليا على ما نحن عليه.
For instance, my little brother,
على سبيل المثال أخي الصغير،
he's very severely autistic.
يعاني من توحد حاد.
He's nonverbal. He can't talk at all.
هو غير لفظي. لا يمكنه التحدث على الإطلاق.
But I love to talk.
لكن أنا أحب أن أتكلم.
People often associate autism
الناس غالبا ما يربطون التوحد
with liking maths and science and nothing else,
بحب الرياضيات والعلوم ولا أي شيء آخر
but I know so many autistic people
لكنني أعرف الكثير من المتوحدين
who love being creative.
ممن يحب أن يكون مبدعا وخلاقا.
But that is a stereotype,
لكن هذه نظرة نمطية.
and the stereotypes of things
والصور النمطية للأشياء
are often, if not always, wrong.
غالبا، وإن لم يكن دائما، خاطئة.
For instance, a lot of people
على سبيل المثال، الكثير من الناس
think autism and think "Rain Man" immediately.
عندما يفكر بالتوحد يفكر ب"رجل المطر" على الفور.
That's the common belief,
هذا هو الاعتقاد السائد،
that every single autistic person is Dustin Hoffman,
أن كل شخص متوحد هو "دستن هفمان"
and that's not true.
وهذا غير صحيح.
But that's not just with autistic people, either.
ولكن هذا لا يحصل مع المتوحدين فقط.
I've seen it with LGBTQ people,
إذ رأيت هذه التصنيفات عند المثليين.
with women, with POC people.
والنساء وذوي البشرة الملونة.
People are so afraid of variety
الناس يخافون جدا من التنوع
that they try to fit everything into a tiny little box
لدرجة أنهم يحاولون وضع كل شيء في صندوق صغير
with really specific labels.
مع تسميات وأصناف محددة.
This is something that actually
هذا شيء
happened to me in real life:
حصل لي فعلا في حياتي على سبيل المثال:
I googled "autistic people are ..."
لقد بحثت في جوجل "المتوحدون هم..."
and it comes up with suggestions
ومن ثم تظهر اقتراحات
as to what you're going to type.
لما كنت ستكتب.
I googled "autistic people are ..."
لقد بحثت في جوجل "المتوحدون هم..."
and the top result was "demons."
وأعلى نتيجة كانت "الشياطين"
That is the first thing that people think
هذا أول شيء يفكر به الناس
when they think autism.
عندما يفكرون بالتوحد.
They know.
هم يعلمون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
One of the things I can do because I'm autistic —
أحد الأشياء التي يمكن أن أقوم بها لأنني متوحدة
it's an ability rather than a disability —
اذ أنها قدرة وليست عجزا
is I've got a very, very vivid imagination.
هو أنه لدي خيال واسع ونشط جدا.
Let me explain it to you a bit.
اسمحوا لي أن أشرح لكم قليلا.
It's like I'm walking in two worlds most of the time.
هو كأنني أمشي في عالمين في معظم الأحيان
There's the real world, the world that we all share,
هناك العالم الحقيقي الذي نتشاركه نحن جميعنا
and there's the world in my mind,
وهناك العالم الذي في ذهني،
and the world in my mind is often so much more real
والعالم الذي في ذهني هو عادة أكثر واقعية بكثير
than the real world.
من العالم الحقيقي.
Like, it's very easy for me to let my mind loose
مثلا، سهل بالنسبة لي ان أطلق العنان لعقلي
because I don't try and fit myself into a tiny little box.
لأني لا أحاول وضع نفسي في صندوق صغير.
That's one of the best things about being autistic.
وهذا من أعظم الأمور حيال كونك متوحدا.
You don't have the urge to do that.
لا تمتلك الرغبة أو الدافع لفعل ذلك.
You find what you want to do,
تجد ما تود إنجازه،
you find a way to do it, and you get on with it.
تجد الطريقة لإنجازه ومن ثم تقوم بإنجازه.
If I was trying to fit myself into a box,
إذا كنت أحاول وضع نفسي في صندوق،
I wouldn't be here, I wouldn't have achieved
لما كنت هنا، ولما تمكنت من إنجاز
half the things that I have now.
نصف ما أنجزته إلى الآن.
There are problems, though.
هناك مشاكل.
There are problems with being autistic,
هناك مشاكل لكونك متوحد.
and there are problems with having too much imagination.
وهناك مشاكل كونه لديك خيال واسع ونشط جدا.
School can be a problem in general,
المدرسة مثلا يمكن أن تكون مشكلة بشكل عام،
but having also to explain to a teacher
لكن وجوب التوضيح للمعلم
on a daily basis
بشكل يومي
that their lesson is inexplicably dull
أن الدرس ممل لسبب غير مفهوم
and you are secretly taking refuge
وتلجأ بشكل سري
in a world inside your head in which you are not in that lesson,
إلى عالم داخل ذهنك وأنك لست مع الدرس
that adds to your list of problems.
هذا يضيف إلى قائمة المشاكل الخاصة بك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Also, when my imagination takes hold,
أيضا، عندما تستحكم مخيلتي،
my body takes on a life of its own.
يتبنى جسدي حياة خاصة بذاته.
When something very exciting happens in my inner world,
عندما يكون هناك شيء مثير للغاية يحدث في عالمي الداخلي،
I've just got to run.
يجب أن أركض.
I've got to rock backwards and forwards,
يجب أن أتحرك جيئة وذهابا.
or sometimes scream.
وبعض الأحيان أن أصرخ.
This gives me so much energy,
هذا يعطيني الكثير من الطاقة،
and I've got to have an outlet for all that energy.
ويجب أن يكون لدي منفذ لكل هذه الطاقة.
But I've done that ever since I was a child,
لكنني كنت أفعل هذا منذ أن كنت طفلة.
ever since I was a tiny little girl.
منذ أن كنت فتاة صغيرة.
And my parents thought it was cute, so they didn't bring it up,
واعتقدت عائلتي أنه ظريف لذلك لم يعيروا الوضع أي اهتمام.
but when I got into school,
لكن عندما بدأت الذهاب الى المدرسة.
they didn't really agree that it was cute.
لم يوافقوا على أنه شيء ظريف.
It can be that people don't want to be friends
من الممكن أن الناس لا تريد أن تصادق
with the girl that starts screaming in an algebra lesson.
مع الفتاة التي تبدأ بالصراح في حصة الجبر.
And this doesn't normally happen in this day and age,
وهذا لا يحصل عادة في الوقت الحاضر.
but it can be that people don't want to be friends with the autistic girl.
لكن من الممكن أن الناس لا يريدون بناء صداقة مع الفتاة المتوحدة.
It can be that people don't want to associate
ومن الممكن أن الناس لا يريدون الاقتران
with anyone who won't or can't fit themselves
مع من لا يريد أو لا يستطيع وضع نفسه
into a box that's labeled normal.
في صندوق مصنف بطبيعي.
But that's fine with me,
لكن لا بأس بذلك بالنسبة لي،
because it sorts the wheat from the chaff,
لأنها تفصل ذوي القدرة عمن سواهم
and I can find which people are genuine and true
وأستطيع أن أجد الاشخاص الغير مزيفين والصادقين
and I can pick these people as my friends.
وأستطيع اختيار هؤلاء الأشخاص كأصدقاء.
But if you think about it, what is normal?
لكن إن فكرت بالأمر، ما هو الطبيعي؟
What does it mean?
ماذا تعني كلمة طبيعي؟
Imagine if that was the best compliment you ever received.
تخيل إن كانت هذه أفضل مجاملة تلقيتها من أي وقت مضى.
"Wow, you are really normal."
"يا للروعة، أنت فعلا طبيعي".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But compliments are,
لكن المجاملات هي،
"you are extraordinary"
"أنت استثنائي"
or "you step outside the box."
أو "أنت تخرج عن المألوف"
It's "you're amazing."
"أنت مدهش"
So if people want to be these things,
لذا ان كان الناس يريدون هذه الأشياء
why are so many people striving to be normal?
إذا لماذا تسعى جاهدة لتكون طبيعية؟
Why are people pouring their brilliant individual light into a mold?
لماذا يصب الناس خلاصة تميزهم الفردي في قالب؟
People are so afraid of variety that they try and force everyone,
الناس يخافون جدا من التنوع لدرجة أنهم يحاولون إجبار الجميع،
even people who don't want to or can't, to become normal.
حتى الأشخاص الذين لا يريدون أو لا يستطيعون على أن يكونوا طبيعيين.
There are camps for LGBTQ people
هناك مخيمات للمثليين
or autistic people to try and make them this "normal,"
أو المتوحدين لمحاولة جعلهم طبيعيين.
and that's terrifying that people would do that in this day and age.
وهذا مخيف إذ أن الناس يحاولون قعل هذا في الوقت الحاضر.
All in all, I wouldn't trade my autism and my imagination for the world.
بشكل عام، لن أقايض توحدي وخيالي بالعالم أجمع.
Because I am autistic,
لأنني متوحدة.
I've presented documentaries to the BBC,
قدمت العديد من الوثائقيات لهيئة الإذاعة البريطانية
I'm in the midst of writing a book,
أنا في خضم تأليف كتاب،
I'm doing this — this is fantastic —
أنا أفعل هذا وهذا رائع
and one of the best things that I've achieved,
وواحدة من أفضل الأشياء التي أنجزتها،
that I consider to have achieved,
والتي اعتبرها قد تحققت،
is I've found ways of communicating
هو أنني وجدت سبلا للتواصل
with my little brother and sister,
مع أخي الصغير وأختي الصغيرة،
who as I've said are nonverbal. They can't speak.
هما وكما وضحت غير لفظيين. لا يستطيعون الكلام.
And people would often write off someone who's nonverbal,
يتخلى البشر في كثير من الأحيان عن الأشخاص الغير لفظيين.
but that's silly, because my little brother and sister
ولكن هذا سخيف، لأن أخي الصغير وأختي
are the best siblings that you could ever hope for.
أفضل الأشقاء الذين قد تأمل وجودهم
They're just the best, and I love them so much
إنهم الأفضل وأنا أحبهم كثيرا.
and I care about them more than anything else.
وأنا أهتم بهم أكثر من أي شيء آخر.
I'm going to leave you with one question:
سأترككم مع سؤال واحد:
If we can't get inside the person's minds,
إذا لم نستطع الدخول إلى عقول الناس،
no matter if they're autistic or not,
سواء كانوا متوحدين أم لا،
instead of punishing anything that strays from normal,
بدلا من معاقبة كل ما هو مختلف،
why not celebrate uniqueness
لم لا نحتفل بالتفرد والتميز
and cheer every time someone unleashes their imagination?
ونشجع كل من أطلق العنان لمخيلته؟
Thank you.
أشكركم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)